M. Susan Schmidt, PhD

(252) 269-0032; susu@starfishnet.com; www.susanschmidt.net

Technical & Developmental Editor, Workshop Leader

Qualifications Summary

Dr. Schmidt is an Editor and Educator with 30 years experience as university and secondary professor of professional communication, science policy, ethics, literature, and writing; and 20 years as government editor and science analyst. She works as contract editor and workshop trainer. She has broad knowledge of curriculum design, grant-writing, conflict resolution and mediation, media, stakeholder outreach, environmental laws, and grammar. She is proficient in analysis of environmental impacts on water quality, wetlands and floodplains, endangered and threatened species. She is fluent in French and German and functional in Spanish. She has active licenses as NC Professional Educator, NC Environmental Educator, and US Coast Guard Captain.

Work History

Polish to Publish, Beaufort, NC Developmental Editor, January 2009 to Present

Advise authors on narrative structure; copyedit. Edited *The Beach Book* by Carl H. Hobbs (VIMS asst. director, Columbia UP): on waves, erosion, sea-level rise. Edited 8 novels, including *Light on Water*, C. L. Rawlins, a New Zealand Maori saga; *Song of Mokihana*, D. P. Matzenik, 1917 Pacific sailing novel. Editor of scientific documents, dissertation proofreader for non-native English speakers. Manuscript-editing, technical, creative-writing workshop leader. Lecturer for NC Humanities on ecological history/ coastal issues. Beaufort Art Center: produce contra-dance, teach creative-writing workshop. Boards: Carteret Local Food Network, NC Maritime Museum Jr. Sailing Program; Beaufort Strategic Planning. For *NC Literary Review 2011*, reviewed NC nature writing; will serve as moderator of NC Literary Homecoming, East Carolina University, September 2011.

University Professor and High School Teacher 1973 to 2009

Taught university technical and creative writing, American literature, creative nonfiction, environmental literature & philosophy, science communication, conflict resolution, environmental policy & community planning, science & religion at Carteret Community College 2001-2008 & 1979-83, Hampton University 2007, Brevard College 1996-2001, Warren Wilson College 1994-95, NC School of Science & Math (as UNC faculty) 1989-94, Duke University 1989-93, College of Charleston 1987-88, NC State University 1983, University of Virginia Engineering School 1979. Taught secondary literature, journalism, French, global environmental issues at Collegiate School in Richmond, VA 1973-76; Philips Academy in Andover, MA 1969 & 1989; SC Governor's School in Charleston 1988. Fellow at NEH Environmental Imagination Institute at Vassar, National Humanities Center, NC Center for Advancement of Teaching, Duke University Environment & English.

Curriculum Designer, Grant-Writer 1976 to 2010

Wrote grants topping \$4 million. Designed interdisciplinary curriculum for Stratford Hall on environmental history, Duke University on environmental philosophy for adults and 9th-graders, Christchurch School on interdisciplinary environmental experiential Chesapeake studies, Brevard College and NC School of Science & Math on environmental humanities, NC State University on humanities for engineering students, and Medical University of South Carolina on AIDS Education and on Medical Ethics for Family Doctors. Lighthouse study, Edenton Historical Commission. Received research grants from National Endowment for the Humanities to design interdisciplinary environmental-humanities curriculum, National Science Foundation on inter-basin water-transfer, Environmental Protection Agency on nonpoint-source-pollution runoff control, Office of Education for land-use/ water-quality workshops, American Association of University Women on Southern Appalachian native plants & traditional music, Fulbright Foundation to teach in West Germany, VA Center for Creative Arts to write in SW France, and NC Arts Council to research Captain John Smith and Jamestown.

USDA Forest Service, Southern Research Station, Asheville, NC, and Atlanta, GA Contract Technical Editor & Workshop Trainer, 1996 to 2008

Edited scientists' journal articles and books, including *Deerskins And Cotton, Ecological Impacts of Historical Land Use in the Central Savannah River Area before 1950* by David White, (USDA Forest Service, 2008); *Ecology and Management of a Forested Landscape, Fifty Years on the Savannah River Site* (Island Press, 2005). Edited *Southern Appalachian Assessment* (Island Press, 1997). Led workshops (in grammar, style, logic, & law) training endangered-species biologists to write legally-defensible environmental-assessment documents. Led grant-writing workshops for scientists; edited silviculture symposia proceedings.

Environmental Scientist/ Policy Analyst/ Editor/ Mediator, 1977 to 2001

For NC Natural Resources Leadership Institute, 1998-2000, mediated between NC Forest Resources & Natural Heritage to protect natural areas and wrote recreational-management plan for 12,000-acre DuPont State Forest. Mediated for Transylvania Dispute Settlement Center, Brevard, NC, 1997-2001. Edited Environmental Science Dictionary, Bruccoli Clark, 1988-91. As Virginia Sea Grant Editor, VIMS, College of William & Mary, 1984-86, edited two monthly newsletters on commercial fishing and marine-science research. Edited *San Diego Log* (waterfront newspaper), 1984. As Environmental Scientist for NC Coastal Management, Morehead City, 1980-82, wrote policy reports and testified to Coastal Resources Commission on land use regulations to protect estuarine water quality, including wetland mitigation, coal ports, oil refineries; wrote grant proposal and management plan to establish NC Estuarine Research Reserve. For Nature Conservancy as steward, wrote Carrot Island Preserve Management Plan, Beaufort, NC, 1979-83; wrote acquisition grant and management plan for Ivy Creek Natural Area, Charlottesville, VA, 1977-79. For US Department of Interior, Washington, 1977, reviewed environmental-impact statements on dams, mediated among departments, and wrote letter signed by Interior Secretary; wrote Executive-Order 11988 Guidelines on Floodplain Management.

Education

Conflict-Resolution Fellow, Natural Resources Leadership Institute, NC State University, 1998-2000
Bioethics, Environmental Philosophy Fellow, Duke University Divinity School, 1990-93
PhD, American Literature, University of South Carolina, 1990
MA, Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 1980 Watershed ecology, water quality Botany study, Highlands (UNC), 1996, Mt. Lake (UVa) biology stations, 1976, 1990
MA, English, University of Virginia, 1972; Teaching License in English, Science (7-12th grades)
BA, English, Connecticut College, May 1971; Oxford University, England, Honors 1969-70

Publications

Dr. Schmidt is the author of *Landfall Along the Chesapeake*, in the Wake of Captain John Smith (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2006) and gave 100 lectures on Chesapeake ecological history. She published 10 journal articles, 150 magazine/ newspaper articles, 7 literary essays, 8 poems, 5 books chapters. She edited 25 technical books, science reports & proceedings, 14 novels & memoirs.

Selected Honors and Awards

VA Center for Creative Arts Fellowship to write in SW France 2008 National Endowment for Humanities Fellowships 1993-94, 1997, AAUW 1999-2000 Most Influential Teacher of 2 highest graduates of NC State University 1994; 12 Brevard College graduates

Member: Coastal Society, Nat. Assoc. of Science Writers, Assoc. for Study of Literature & Environment

Recent Travel

Volunteer Bird Survey/ Conservation work in Kenya, winter 2011. Walked 450 miles on Camino de Santiago in Spain and France, 2007-08. Trekked in New Zealand, Winters 2008 & 2010. Kayaked 500 miles in Alaska, kayaked 400 miles with Brevard students in NC & SC. Delivered sailboats to West Indies, 1980s.